The Bailey Collection
The Bailey Collection
- Miscellaneous notes, transcripts and original documents, 16th century-19th century; GB/418/C.7.26, 29, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43; GB/418/Bailey/6; Chetham's Library
  - Notes fromThe antiquities of Canterbury by William Somner and Nicolas Battely (London, 1703)., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 13; GB/418/Bailey/6/53; Chetham's Library
    SeeThe antiquities of Canterbury.: In two parts. The first part. The antiquities of Canterbury; or a survey of that ancient city, with the suburbs and cathedral, &c. Sought out and published by the industry and good will of William Somner. The second edition, revised and enlarged by Nicolas Battely, M.A. also Mr. Somner's Discourse called Chartham-News: Or a relation of some strange bones found at Chartham in Kent. To which are added some observations concerning the Roman antiquities of Canterbury. And a preface, giving an account of the works and remains of the learned antiquary Mr. William Somner, by N.B. The second part. Cantuaria sacra: or the antiquities I. Of the Cathedral and metropolitical church. II. Of the Archbishoprick. III. Of the late Priory of Christ-Church; and of the present Collegiate Church, founded by K. Hen. VIII. With a catalogue of all the Deans and Canons thereof. IV. Of the Monastery of St. Augustin; of the parish-churches, hospitals, and other religious places, that are or have been in or near that city; / enquired into, by Nicholas Battely, Vicar of Beaksborn. Illustrated and adorned with several useful and fair sculptures.
  - Notes entitled ‘Ex continuiatione Polychronici MSS, penes dominu de Weymouth’, being extracts from thePolychronicon., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 14; GB/418/Bailey/6/54; Chetham's Library
    Polychronicon
  - Some account of Sir Jacob Ackworth by Thomas Bayly., nd [?19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 15; GB/418/Bailey/6/55; Chetham's Library
  - Account of journey to Tadmor by Mr Hallifax, also notes on Greek inscriptions found there., (1691-1692); GB/418/C.7.43 no 16; GB/418/Bailey/6/56; Chetham's Library
  - Document entitled ‘Promoc[i]one Eccl[es]iastica infra Diocesin Eborac in donacione Domini Regis’, being an account of benefices in the diocese of York comparing their ‘comen reputed value’ and their ‘value in the king’s bookes’, and listing the incumbents., (1664-1680); GB/418/C.7.43 no 17; GB/418/Bailey/6/57; Chetham's Library
    Those individuals listed were incumbents in the parishes between 1664 and 1683.
  - 19th century transcription of a bull of Pope Urban VIII dated 1631 (in Latin)., GB/418/C.7.43 no 18; GB/418/Bailey/6/58; Chetham's Library
  - Notes on the Gunpowder Plot of 1605., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 19; GB/418/Bailey/6/59; Chetham's Library
  - A document entitled ‘For the better informinge of a Traviler in the estate of any premise or c[o]untry it shalbe necessary for him to consider’ such as ‘the country (including soil and fertility), the people (including number and quality), and the policy and government (including nobility and the sovereign)'., [?16th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 20; GB/418/Bailey/6/60; Chetham's Library
  - Certificate of burial of Joshua Turner of Battersea., 1813; GB/418/C.7.43 no 21; GB/418/Bailey/6/61; Chetham's Library
  - An account itemising ‘Gazing for the Corporation at Sc[h]ool’ as well as ‘new quarels’, and ‘casments’ with one of them ‘pind on the irons’. The account was ‘allowed by Sam[ue]l Brooke’., 12 Dec 1727; GB/418/C.7.43 no 22; GB/418/Bailey/6/62; Chetham's Library
  - Receipt from Thomas Hunt, preacher at Oldham, to James Ashton for £12 10s., 18 Apr 1611; GB/418/C.7.43 no 23; GB/418/Bailey/6/63; Chetham's Library
  - A document being the ‘Examination’ of Elizabeth, wife of John Andrews of Ashton-under-Lyne, taken on oath before one of the JPs for the West Riding of Yorkshire on 18 May 1750, relating to her husband, his settlement in Ashton-under-Lyne, and her need for poor relief., GB/418/C.7.43 no 24; GB/418/Bailey/6/64; Chetham's Library
  - Certificate of marriage banns of Nicholas Fletcher and Hannah Winterbottom of Wortley., 3 Jun 1707; GB/418/C.7.43 no 25; GB/418/Bailey/6/65; Chetham's Library
  - Receipt from William Assheton of Chadderton to Sir Peter Leigh for £5., 3 Jun 1615; GB/418/C.7.43 no 26; GB/418/Bailey/6/66; Chetham's Library
  - Receipt from William Flathers to Hamon L'Estrange for £15., 6 Nov 1635; GB/418/C.7.43 no 27; GB/418/Bailey/6/67; Chetham's Library
  - Receipt from John Pratt to Mr Watts for £44. Arrears of rent due to Fellows of Trinity College., 10 Oct 1644; GB/418/C.7.43 no 28; GB/418/Bailey/6/68; Chetham's Library
  - 19th century notes on costs of repairs to Barnwell Abbey., (Mid 17th century); GB/418/C.7.43 no 29; GB/418/Bailey/6/69; Chetham's Library
  - Extract from rental of Kirkstall Abbey, co Yorks., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 30; GB/418/Bailey/6/70; Chetham's Library
  - Choice of Mr Seymour as Speaker for the Parliament of 1677., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 31; GB/418/Bailey/6/71; Chetham's Library
  - 19th century notes on the rights of the Crown to salt marshes., [?17th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 32; GB/418/Bailey/6/72; Chetham's Library
  - Account of the Palace of the King of Naples., (1742); GB/418/C.7.43 no 33; GB/418/Bailey/6/73; Chetham's Library
    Includes descriptions of a painting recently rescued from Herculaneum.
  - Copy of a letter from Edmund Chishull to Sir Charles Mordaunt concerning a Greek inscription in the possession of the Earl of Pembroke., 1732; GB/418/C.7.43 no 34; GB/418/Bailey/6/74; Chetham's Library
  - Readings noted in Plato'sRepublic., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 35; GB/418/Bailey/6/75; Chetham's Library
    Republic
  - Record of events in England 1683-1705, chiefly ecclesiastical preferments., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 36; GB/418/Bailey/6/76; Chetham's Library
  - Lists of Deans etc., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 37; GB/418/Bailey/6/77; Chetham's Library
    List of Deans of St Pauls to 1540, St Asaph to 1534 and Winchester.
    List of Prebendaries of Winchester.
    List of Chancellors or Vicars General, Winchester.
    List of Archdeacons of Winchester and Surrey.
    List of Deans and Prebendaries of Canterbury.
    List of Archdeacons of Canterbury.
    List of Masters or Wardens of St. Thomas's Hospital.
    List of Vicars of Northallerton.
    Taxatio Ecclesiasticae Anglice et Wallice (auctoritate P. Nicholai). (1802). Extracts from Preface.
    Account of Dulwich College (FromThe Gentleman's Magazine).
    Russel family, Dukes and Earls of Bedford. Burial place.
    List of the Priors of Belvoir, Leicestershire.
    Some account of Fulmodestone Rectory, Norfolk.
    Extracts from Registers of Ingleby Manor, Cleveland, Coxwold, Yorks (Layton family), Kirkdale, Yorks (Gibson, Robinson etc), Husthwaite cum Carlton, Yorks, Birdforth, Yorks (Tomlinson etc).
    List of rectors of Whitburn, Durham, Bolden (Durham), Bishopweremouth, Sunderland, Gateshead, Haughton, Haughton le Spring, Washington, Ryton and Stanhope.
    Perpetual Curates of Chester-le-Street.
    Vicars of Stockton.
  - Proposals from inhabitants of Beursell concerning their grinding corn at Ryton Mill., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 38; GB/418/Bailey/6/78; Chetham's Library
  - Extracts relating to Somerset, Dorset, Wilts etc from Thomas Madox'sHistory of the Exchequer., nd [19th century]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 39; GB/418/Bailey/6/79; Chetham's Library
    History of the Exchequer
    The history and antiquities of the Exchequer of the Kings of England, in two periods:: to wit, from the Norman conquest, to the end of the reign of K. John; and from the end of the reign of K. John, to the end of the reign of K. Edward II: taken from records.
    See Thomas Madox (1666-1727),The history and antiquities of the Exchequer of the Kings of England, in two periods:: to wit, from the Norman conquest, to the end of the reign of K. John; and from the end of the reign of K. John, to the end of the reign of K. Edward II: taken from records. (London, 1711).
  - Correspondence concerning the claim to the estates of Sir Andrew Chadwick (d 1768)., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 40; GB/418/Bailey/6/80; Chetham's Library
    From the papers of Sir Charles Young, Garter King of Arms, sold with his Library by Sotheby's [18 December 1871]. Printed by R. C. Christie in Bailey'sPalatine Note-Book, vol iv (1884) pp 61-2.
  - Papers concerning James Dodsley and Thomas English., 18th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 41; GB/418/Bailey/6/81; Chetham's Library
    Receipts for money received for compiling the Annual Register 1768-92.
    Dodsley and S Hoole: assignment of rights in a book written by Hoole.
    Dodsley and Thomas Wright (printer): agreement as to printing.
    Letter of Bennet of Chinley 20 January 1745.
    Note on antiquaries' views of William I's conquest of England.
    Lines to John Dryden.
  - Collection of miscellaneous prose and poetry., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.43 no 42; GB/418/Bailey/6/82; Chetham's Library
    Copied [at the beginning of the nineteenth century]. Some portions are written by or on members of the Burney family.
  - "Book of Remembrance for Sr Richard Scotts occasions by Gervas Watts beginneinge in Marche 1637.", [1637 & 1803]; GB/418/C.7.43 no 43; GB/418/Bailey/6/83; Chetham's Library
    a) Curious account book dealing mostly with records of purchases of 'pipestaves' at various places in Ireland during 1637 and 1638. 'Pipestaves' were probably tobacco pipes and were sold at £4 5s to £10 per 1,000. (Extracts published inManchester Geneologist, April 1992.) b) Printed poems on the threatened invasion of England by the French, 1803.
  - Index of clergy in Lancashire, mostly 17th century., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.39 bundle 40; GB/418/Bailey/6/84; Chetham's Library
    A-Z index on cards stored in an archive box.
    In the catalogue of 1890 John Cree described this as "a very valuable Index, in slips, of Lancashire & Cheshire clergymen, mostly of the 17th century, containing about 3000 names."
  - Manuscript notes (some shorthand) and pedigrees of Ralph Brideoake (Brideoak), master and feoffee of Chetham's Hospital., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 3, bundle 21; GB/418/Bailey/6/85; Chetham's Library
    Notes and manuscript index to Bagshaw'sDe Spiritualisus Pecci.
  - Bundle of slips containing an index to Randle Holme'sAcademy of Armory., (1688); GB/418/C.7.28 no 4; GB/418/Bailey/6/86; Chetham's Library
    Academy of Armory
    The academy of armory, or, A storehouse of armory and blazon.: Containing the several variety of created beings, and how born in coats of arms, both foreign and domestick. With the instruments used in all trades and sciences, together with their terms of art. Also the etymologies, definitions, and historical observations on the same, explicated and explained according to our modern language. Very usefel [sic] for all gentlemen, scholars, divines, and all such as desire any knowledge in arts and sciences. / By Randle Holme, of the city of Chester, gentleman sewer in extraordinary to his late Majesty King Charles 2. And sometimes depurty for the Kings of Arms
    See Randle Holme (1627-1699),The academy of armory, or, A storehouse of armory and blazon.: Containing the several variety of created beings, and how born in coats of arms, both foreign and domestick. With the instruments used in all trades and sciences, together with their terms of art. Also the etymologies, definitions, and historical observations on the same, explicated and explained according to our modern language. Very usefel [sic] for all gentlemen, scholars, divines, and all such as desire any knowledge in arts and sciences. / By Randle Holme, of the city of Chester, gentleman sewer in extraordinary to his late Majesty King Charles 2. And sometimes depurty for the Kings of Arms. (Chester, 1688).
  - Fragments of a printed 19th century text ofThe School Candidates, a Prosaic Burlesque, by Henry Clarke (1743-1818), Schoolmaster of Salford., GB/418/C.7.29 no 3; GB/418/Bailey/6/87; Chetham's Library
    The School Candidates, a Prosaic Burlesque
    The school candidates: a prosaic burlesque. Occasioned by the election of a schoolmaster at the village of Stretford, near Manchester, 18th January, 1788 / by Henry Clarke, LL. D.; reprinted from the original, and edited, with a memoir of the author, &c. &c., by John Eglington Bailey, F.S.A
    With collection of notes on Clarke's life and works.
    SeeThe school candidates: a prosaic burlesque. Occasioned by the election of a schoolmaster at the village of Stretford, near Manchester, 18th January, 1788 / by Henry Clarke, LL. D.; reprinted from the original, and edited, with a memoir of the author, &c. &c., by John Eglington Bailey, F.S.A. (Manchester, 1877).
  - Notes on the case of the supposed demonaic possession of the Starkie family of Cleworth Hall in Leigh parish, 1594-6., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.29 no 4; GB/418/Bailey/6/88; Chetham's Library
    Transcription of John Darrell'sTrue Narration of the Strange and Grevous Vexation by the devil of 7 persons in Lancashire and William Somers of Nottingham.
    Bundle is labelled "Leigh Devils".
  - Bundle relating to William Ryley, Lancaster Herald (bur 1667), and the Ryley family., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 bundle 28; GB/418/Bailey/6/89; Chetham's Library
- Letters to James Crossley and letters relating to Archbishop Harsnett, (18th century)-19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 nos 1-10; GB/418/Bailey/7; Chetham's Library
  - Letters from Thomas Rodd to James Crossley, with bills and accounts., 1835-1848; GB/418/C.7.27 no 1; GB/418/Bailey/7/1; 1 bundle; Chetham's Library
    The letters contain many details about sales, books and catalogues.
  - 19th century transcriptions of Francis Hooper's correspondence with John Byrom., (1716-1726); GB/418/C.7.27 no 2; GB/418/Bailey/7/2; bundle; Chetham's Library
    Contains many references to affairs at Cambridge University and to Bentley, a noted classical scholar.
  - Bundle of letters from Rev J. B. Hunter, Rev R. Parkinson, Sir A. W. Woods, J. O. Halliwell, Theodore Williams, R. Tongue, and Rev C. D. Wray, probably all sent to Canon Raines., 1854-1870; GB/418/C.7.27 no 3; GB/418/Bailey/7/3; bundle; Chetham's Library
  - Bundle of letters to Canon Raines from correspondents whose surnames begin with the letter G., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 no 4; GB/418/Bailey/7/4; bundle; Chetham's Library
  - Bundle of letters to Canon Raines from Thomas Heywood, John Keble, James Kendrick, S. W. King and J. H. Markland., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 no 5; GB/418/Bailey/7/5; bundle; Chetham's Library
  - Bundle of letters to and from several correspondents concerning biographies of Archbishop Harset and Rev A. Harsnet., 1860s; GB/418/C.7.27 no 6; GB/418/Bailey/7/6; bundle; Chetham's Library
    The letters are in their original envelopes which have 'penny red' stamps.
  - Bundle of letters to James Crossley from various correspondents including Rev J. Pickford., 1830s-1870s; GB/418/C.7.27 no 7; GB/418/Bailey/7/7; Chetham's Library
    Letters from Rev J. Pickford date 1840s-1860s.
  - Transcription of Dr John Worthington's diary and correspondence made for James Crossley and printed in Chetham Society volumes 13, 36 and 114., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 no 8; GB/418/Bailey/7/8; Chetham's Library
  - Alphabetical list of ministers [?members of Westminster Assembly of Divines] with biographical notes., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 no 9; GB/418/Bailey/7/9; Chetham's Library
    Includes some Lancashire clergy.
  - Proof sheets of Dr Worthington's diary and correspondence published by the Chetham Society., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.27 no 10; GB/418/Bailey/7/10; Chetham's Library
    List of names of [?Westminster Assembly of Divines]. Labelled "Bailey MSS No. 20".
- Notes etc relating to Lewis Bayl[e]y author ofThe practice of pietie: directing a Christian how to walke that he may please God., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 nos 1 & 2; GB/418/Bailey/8; Chetham's Library
  The practice of pietie: directing a Christian how to walke that he may please God
  The practice of pietie: directing a Christian how to walke that he may please God.
  The practice of pietie
  - Book containing notes on the family, career and writings of Lewis Bayl[e]y (1565-1632), author ofThe practice of pietie: directing a Christian how to walke that he may please God., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 1, bundle 23; GB/418/Bailey/8/1; Chetham's Library
    Manuscript and printed notes.
  - Manuscript notes on editions of Lewis Bayl[e]y'sThe practice of pietie and printer's galley proofs of J. E. Bailey's article on Bayl[e]y., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 2, bundle 23; GB/418/Bailey/8/2; 1 bundle; Chetham's Library
- Notes relating to Cheshire and Chester city, 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 nos 5-7; GB/418/Bailey/9; Chetham's Library
  - Bundle of notes on 17th century Chester., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 5, bundle 24; GB/418/Bailey/9/1; Chetham's Library
  - Bundle of notes relating to people and places in Cheshire., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 6, bundle 24; GB/418/Bailey/9/2; Chetham's Library
    Birkenhead, John
    Bunbury Church
    Frodsham
    Halton, by Lee, a poem
    Handforth Hall, printed account
    Jackson, Rev of Nether and Over Church
    Jacobson, Bishop, printed account
    Macclesfield
    Mottram Andrews, Sale of Manor
    Nantwich
    Parker, John and hisTrue Pattern of Piety
    Rostherne
    Savage pedigree
    Warmincham
    Wasse, Thomas and Stockport Church
    Wilmslow Brass
  - Bundle of notes relating to people and places in Cheshire., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 7, bundle 24; GB/418/Bailey/9/3; Chetham's Library
    List of ancient charters relating to Cheshire and Lancashire with prices.
    Commissioners of Array
    A Custom of Cheshire
    Hearth Tax
    The Cheshire Hunt with notes
    Mead'sCheshire Journey
    Meredith manuscripts and undated deeds of
    "Newes out of Cheshire"
    Subsidies
    "Cheshire's Successe"
    Taxatio Ecclesiastice, Extracts from
    Towns, description of
    Cheshire books, poems, bibliography, portraits, chiefly printed
    Cheshire Sheaf
    Miscellaneous notes
- Notes relating to Leigh Grammar School, (15th century)-19th century; GB/418/C.7.29 nos 1 & 2; GB/418/Bailey/10; Chetham's Library
  - Slips pasted onto individual sheets of paper containing Bailey's printed catalogue of the library of Leigh Grammar School., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.29 no 1; GB/418/Bailey/10/1; 1 bundle; Chetham's Library
  - Bailey's own copy of his history of Leigh Grammar School., (15th century)-19th century; GB/418/C.7.29 no 2; GB/418/Bailey/10/2; Chetham's Library
    Also large collection of miscellaneous notes on Leigh, especially its church and Grammar School. Transcripts of deeds relating to Leigh area, 14th -17th centuries. Transcription of 1524 Lay Subsidy for Leigh.
- Notes relating to people called Bailey, 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 8; GB/418/Bailey/11; Chetham's Library
  - Collection of miscellaneous notes relating to people called Bailey., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.28 no 8; GB/418/Bailey/11/1; Chetham's Library
- Material relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church, 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30; GB/418/Bailey/12; Chetham's Library
  - Notes concerning Thomas G. Law relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 1; GB/418/Bailey/12/1; Chetham's Library
    Letters to J. E. Bailey on research and printing of Law's edition of Laurence Vaux's Catechism for the Chetham Society (Chetham Society, NS 4). Letters dated 26 February 1884 - 6 May 1885.
    6 undated letters: Law to Bailey.
    2 postcards: Law to Bailey - postmarked Edinburgh, 21 March 1885; 6 April 1885.
    Note (titled) "Wanted". List of materials needed by Law.
    Letter dated 2 November 1883: Law to Bailey (in shorthand). Stuck to memorandum G. W. Napier to J. E. Bailey. 27 December 1883.
  - Cuttings relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 2 (a); GB/418/Bailey/12/2; Chetham's Library
    i)Manchester Guardian 9 April 1885.
    Notice of forthcoming meeting of the Lancashire & Cheshire Antiquarian Society, ie Bailey lecture on Vaux documents.
    ii)Manchester Guardian, 16 April 1885.
    Including report of Bailey lecture and gift to Chetham's Library.
    iii) Undated, unidentified: report of Bailey lecture and gift.
    iv) Ditto, with manuscript note in ink appended to cutting "Well done Vaux! He saw the thieves were coming".
    v)The Scotsman 21 May 1885.
    Review of Law's edition of Vaux's Catechism.(CS NS 4)
    vi)The Edinburgh Courant 19 June 1885.
    Review of Law's edition of Vaux's Catechism.
    vii)The Church Intelligencer 1 October 1885.
    Review of N. Pocock'sTroubles connected with the Prayer book of 1549 (Camden Soc 1884)
    viii) Cutting(s) mounted on papers marked Vaux 1; Vaux 2. Copies of (iii).
    ix) Cutting(s) mounted on papers and marked Mottram 1; Mottram 2; Mottram 3. Report of J. E. Bailey paper on Mottram-in-Longdendale (source unidentified; nd).
    x) Cutting mounted on paper (headed ms pencil note "Will this be right? C. W. Sutton").
    Report of J. E. Bailey on Writ of Privy Seal granting permission to Abbot and Convent of Whalley to fortify their buildings (source unidentified; nd).
  - Proofs ofA catechisme, or Christian doctrine, by Lawrence Vaux, B.D., canon regular and sub-prior of St. Martin's monastery, Louvain, sometime warden of the collegiate church, Manchester. Reprinted from an edition of 1583, ed. Thomas Law, Chetham Society New Series 4 (1885)., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 2 (b); GB/418/Bailey/12/3; Chetham's Library
    A catechisme, or Christian doctrine, by Lawrence Vaux, B.D., canon regular and sub-prior of St. Martin's monastery, Louvain, sometime warden of the collegiate church, Manchester. Reprinted from an edition of 1583
    Proofs of the 41st and 42nd reports of the Council of the Chetham Society.
  - Transcripts relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 2 (c); GB/418/Bailey/12/4; Chetham's Library
    Transcript: Extract from the Rambler vol VIII, pp 408-410.
    Article on Laurence Vaux (by Richard Simpson) (8 pages, writing on 3).
    Transcript: Marginal note - Chronicum Martinianum vol 1, p. 270.Rambler, December 1857.
    f 1r-3r: Letter of Laurence Vaux to the Prior of St. Martins, Louvain.
    f 3v-4v: Shorthand (in pencil) - headed "Vaux" (in ink).
    f 5v: Vaux (in ink).
    Extracts from article on Vaux inRambler: December 1857 (in hand of T. G. Law).
  - Letters relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 2 (d); GB/418/Bailey/12/5; Chetham's Library
    a) Copy of an account of the discovery by Ed van Even in 1855 of Vaux papers in a baker's shop in Louvain (3p). In French.
    b) Translation of above by C. Collman (5 p).
    c) Copy? of account of discovery (see (a))
    Three letters from Ed van Even to J. E. Bailey dated 26 February 1885; 4 March 1885 (in envelope); 14 March 1885.
    Stencil of letter: Bailey to Ed van Even, 28 February 1885.
    Draft of letter: Bailey to Ed van Even, nd [?Dec 1884].
    Draft of letter: Bailey to Ed van Even, nd.
    Letter: C. Collman to Bailey 11 March 1885: On Subscription fund for purchase of the Vaux manuscripts including a note by Bailey on subscribers and sums promised.
    Letter: W. Reynell to Bailey 29 October 1884: On members of the Vaux family in Ireland.
    Letter: J. C. Price to [?Bailey] Record Office 24/1/78: On Vol 10 Dom S Eliz [ie Calendar of state papers, domestic series]: 1559.
  - Miscellaneous notes relating to Laurence Vaux, Warden of Manchester Collegiate Church., 19th century; GB/418/C.7.30 no 3; GB/418/Bailey/12/6; Chetham's Library